<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Capital Ideas</title>
  <subtitle>Reflections of Matt Olson</subtitle>
  <id>http://mattolson.com/</id>
  <link href="http://mattolson.com/"/>
  <link href="http://mattolson.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2013-06-17T13:55:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Matt Olson</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Nothing To Hide?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2013/06/17/nothing-to-hide/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/06/17/nothing-to-hide/</id>
    <published>2013-06-17T13:55:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-06-17T13:55:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Free Speech Movement" height="235" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/savio.jpg" width="300" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be clear to everyone by now that the National Security Agency (NSA) has achieved an unprecedented level of access to the communication patterns 
and digital trails of American citizens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact details are murky due to the classified nature of the program and the public relations denials of the companies involved (including Apple, Google, 
Microsoft, and Facebook), but the best information we have at this time is that PRISM is an NSA program for streamlining Foreign Intelligence Surveillance 
Act (FISA) requests with these companies, and receiving data in return. The companies claim that the NSA does not have direct access to their servers, and 
information is only delivered after a lawfully issued FISA request, and is not delivered in an automated fashion. This might be comforting, if it weren’t 
for the fact that the FISA courts have largely rubber stamped any request the government makes on national security grounds. With the passage of the FISA 
Amendments Acts of 2008, it is easier than ever to get a court order for expansive datasets on the shakiest of foundations.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Free Speech Movement" height="235" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/savio.jpg" width="300" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be clear to everyone by now that the National Security Agency (NSA) has achieved an unprecedented level of access to the communication patterns 
and digital trails of American citizens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact details are murky due to the classified nature of the program and the public relations denials of the companies involved (including Apple, Google, 
Microsoft, and Facebook), but the best information we have at this time is that PRISM is an NSA program for streamlining Foreign Intelligence Surveillance 
Act (FISA) requests with these companies, and receiving data in return. The companies claim that the NSA does not have direct access to their servers, and 
information is only delivered after a lawfully issued FISA request, and is not delivered in an automated fashion. This might be comforting, if it weren’t 
for the fact that the FISA courts have largely rubber stamped any request the government makes on national security grounds. With the passage of the FISA 
Amendments Acts of 2008, it is easier than ever to get a court order for expansive datasets on the shakiest of foundations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NSA’s reach goes far beyond the newly revealed PRISM program. In 2006, whistleblower Mark Klein revealed that the NSA has a top secret room in an AT&amp;amp;T 
facility in San Francisco that gives them direct, realtime access to all traffic on its backbone network. It has since been revealed that over a dozen such 
rooms exist in major facilities across the country, giving the NSA wiretapping capabilities for nearly all Internet traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a lot to say on the subject of Internet surveillance—too much for this space, in fact—so let me be brief. The Internet is arguably the most important 
communication medium in human history. The open communication and democratization of information made possible by the Internet has been transformative for 
societies across the globe. When central governments build surveillance (or control) capacity over these critical tools, it makes its citizens (that’s you and me)
vulnerable to abuses unimaginable just 20 years ago. We need only take a page from history and look to the abuses of the FBI during the reign of J. Edgar Hoover 
to catch of glimpse of what’s possible. He used his immense authority to stifle Vietnam War protests, and the Free Speech and Civil Rights movements, infiltrate 
and sow dissent within these movements, which were seen as directly challenging government authority, and discredit or embarrass political leaders and personal enemies.
Imagine if Hoover were tapping not just the phones calls of Martin Luther King, Jr., but his emails and location, as well as those of his associates and followers. 
It would have been much more difficult, if not impossible to organize the protests that expanded our rights and ended a senseless war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, getting lost in this discussion is another, perhaps even more disturbing, revelation that came to light a few days prior to the PRISM leak. An order by 
the FISA court obtained by the Guardian demands that Verizon (and its subsidiary Verizon Wireless) hand over “comprehensive communication routing information” 
for all of its customers, including for calls entirely within the United States, to the NSA on a continual, daily basis. This does not include the name and address of
the customer, and this “anonymization” is one of the ways that these broad collection orders make it through the court. However, the information does include the 
handset ID and cell tower IDs. Using a process known as trilateration, the location of the person making the call can be calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this important if they don’t actually know who is making the call? According to a report published in Nature in March 2013, human mobility traces are highly 
unique. We all have our own fingerprint of sorts, and relatively few data points are required to uniquely identify an individual. Futher, the world we live in today 
is awash with data. Numerous companies, such as Acxiom and Datalogix, compile massive datasets on consumer behavior. Built for marketing purposes, these databases
correlate information from numerous sources to build profiles of individuals and their behavior. For example, Facebook now uses obfuscated versions of their users’ 
email addresses and phone numbers to correlate with Datalogix to learn about your purchasing behavior, so now the companies can connect what ads you see on Facebook 
with what you buy in brick and mortar retail stores. Of course, this is all done for marketing and advertising, but these, and many other, databases are also
available to the NSA, making it possible to potentially correlate rich identity information with location tracking from phone records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in the era of Big Data. Some of the world’s top data scientists are gathering at two enormous new NSA facilities in Maryland and Utah to work with unprecedented 
volumes of data — Internet activity, phone records, realtime and historical data, government and commercially available data — building profiles of individuals and 
looking for patterns, attempting to root out terrorists. I have no doubt that such information is valuable in identifying patterns that might look suspicious.
It is also useful for other purposes. The real trouble is the complete lack of transparency and oversight of these programs. We are told that everything is done with 
Congressional oversight, yet members briefed on these programs are unable to talk about them outside of closed hearings due to their classified nature, making it 
effectively impossible for them to represent us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Democracy requires an informed citizenry to function properly. Transparency and accountability are essential to that goal. We must declassify surveillance programs 
conducted against American citizens and reopen debate on the Patriot Act so we can make an informed decision as a society on the proper balance of liberty and security.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Reinventing Chico</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2013/04/29/reinventing-chico/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/04/29/reinventing-chico/</id>
    <published>2013-04-29T14:03:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-04-29T14:03:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Fab Lab" height="200" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/fablab.jpg" width="300" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A group of makers has been quietly building a community space here in Chico with great potential for democratizing the tools of innovation and expression. 
After months of planning and hard work, Idea Fab Labs, Chico’s first makerspace, is opening its doors May 4th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Makerspaces—open, social spaces designed for brainstorming, collaborative learning, tool sharing, and most importantly, making things—have a long tradition 
in technology communities around the world. They provide the space and both standard and high-tech tools, as well as the knowledge of how to use them, in a 
collaborative, open environment where experimentation and peer-to-peer learning thrives.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Fab Lab" height="200" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/fablab.jpg" width="300" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A group of makers has been quietly building a community space here in Chico with great potential for democratizing the tools of innovation and expression. 
After months of planning and hard work, Idea Fab Labs, Chico’s first makerspace, is opening its doors May 4th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Makerspaces—open, social spaces designed for brainstorming, collaborative learning, tool sharing, and most importantly, making things—have a long tradition 
in technology communities around the world. They provide the space and both standard and high-tech tools, as well as the knowledge of how to use them, in a 
collaborative, open environment where experimentation and peer-to-peer learning thrives.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technology-driven maker culture, both inside companies and outside of them, is responsible for many of the innovations we take for granted today. Steve Wozniak, 
the original developer of the Apple computer, did most of his work on that seminal design to impress his friends at the Homebrew Computer Club, a Palo Alto based 
group of home electronics hobbyists. It is that enthusiastic spirit of open innovation and knowledge sharing that forms the basis of the maker culture, and has
inspired the recent resurgence in makerspaces around the world. (Makerspaces are sometimes known as hackerspaces, although the term “hacker” in this context has 
nothing to do with the image you might have of criminal activity, instead referring to the original meaning of the word: a spirit of tinkering, modifying, and 
extending existing hardware and software.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="chicorsquos-makerspace"&gt;Chico’s Makerspace&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Idea Fab Labs has taken the makerspace concept one step further by offering a much wider range of modern tools than are traditionally available: an industrial laser cutter, 
a CNC router, a 3D printer, textile and leatherworking equipment, a wood shop, and a metal shop, in addition to the standard microelectronics workshop. It is a digital 
fabrication facility, giving the community an opportunity to work with specialized tools that are ordinarily out of reach for hobbyists or small businesses,
learn how to use them, and build prototypes of their ideas, either for personal or commercial purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Idea Fab Labs sprang from a collaboration between Erin and Kristina Banwell, Jordan Layman, Billy Hopkins, and Sean Mitchell, all Chicoans who embody the maker spirit. 
After visiting makerspaces elsewhere and seeing the amazing work they’ve published online, they wanted to build the ultimate makerspace here in Chico. Rather than waiting 
for someone else to come along and do it, they and their friends got their hands dirty renovating an industrial space south of campus, buying equipment and finding like-minded 
collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What motivates these guys to put in all those long hours? According to Erin, “There’s a worldwide movement that is taking the form of makerspaces and hackerspaces and these groups 
that are collaborating together, open source over the Internet, and in person, and we are just a part of this worldwide movement. What that movement represents is a new paradigm 
in innovation, manufacturing, and organizational structure, all falling under the banner of Open Source. We’re carrying the torch.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The widespread availability of information, hardware and software designs, source code, and scientific data openly available on the Internet has led to an explosion of 
innovation in recent years, and it’s never been easier for a self-motivated individual to apply what they’ve learned by building on the work of others. In the software 
and hardware world, this is known as Open Source. As opposed to the traditional system of locking up information behind patents for monopolization, Open Source software 
and hardware designs make the results of your innovations freely available for others to build on, usually with little or no licensing restrictions. This has sped up rate 
of innovation to unprecedented levels—clearly a net benefit for society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it’s often more efficient to share information in person, especially when troubleshooting a problem in an area where you are inexperienced. It’s easy to get 
discouraged and decide to move on. For this reason, makerspaces have turned into a powerful force for learning outside academia. Sharing your skills and learning from 
your peers is seen as one of the key purposes of makerspaces, and Idea Fab Labs is no exception. A community of makers is already using the space to work together
in a spirit of mutual assistance. In addition to the type of informal peer-to-peer education that already takes place at the lab, structured classes will be offered 
on a wide variety of topics by local experts. As Erin told me, “If someone wants to learn how to use a 3D printer, or a laser cutter, or a CNC router, or they want to 
learn how to write code in C++, or Javascript, or Ruby on Rails, this is a place that is going to provide that, outside the institutional educational structure.
We are creating a place where, whether you are already a tech person, or you have no knowledge of it whatsoever, you are welcome to come and work and learn.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For small businesses, the advantages of prototyping at Idea Fab Labs are clear. In the prototyping stage, it is not uncommon to go through dozens of iterations before 
perfecting your design for manufacture. To purchase high end prototyping equipment for a speculative venture, not to mention the space and electricity to use it, would 
be prohibitively expensive for most small businesses, but having it available on a rental basis at low cost, not to mention having other smart individuals to bounce ideas 
off of and troubleshoot problems, is a clear advantage. The lone inventor previously discouraged from testing out his/her designs because of high initial costs can now 
begin a rapid prototyping cycle, perhaps using the result for fundraising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-art-gallery"&gt;The Art Gallery&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tools available at the lab are just that: tools. It is up to the individual how to use them. Artists have begun to discover these tools and are developing fascinating 
new modes of expression. The lab wants to make these tools and the knowledge of how to use them available not just to left brain types, but righties as well, in an ongoing 
exploration of the intersection of art and technology. In explaining the motivation behind the gallery, Erin explains, “we want to showcase some of the possibilities of 
digital fabrication, and to push the boundaries of art with this technology.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is possible when a talented conceptual artist is given all the tools in the lab and training on how to use them? There’s only one way to find out. In that spirit of 
experimentation, Idea Fab Labs has established a residency program for established artists to train on this new equipment and follow their muse. The program includes two 
weeks at the lab, training by experts, a creative environment to do their work, followed by an exhibition in the gallery. (Turns out there is plenty of space for an art 
gallery in the lab’s 7,000 sq ft facility.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first such artist residency is in progress. David Seied, a computational/architectural 3D designer from Denver is working with Erin to discover what these tools can 
add to his already impressive body of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seied works with 3D modeling software to create complex geometric shapes. He is becoming well-known for his designs printed in steel and sandstone. He worked as an intern 
for Marc Fornes and THEVERYMANY, an impressive computational architecture project, on an installation at the Denver Botanic Gardens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gallery opening for the Seied exhibit will be held on May 4th at Idea Fab Labs (603 Orange Street) from 3-6pm. Anyone interested in Seied’s art or the lab itself is 
welcome to drop in. Art will be available for purchase. Following the opening, the exhibit will be open to the public through June 1st.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="building-a-tech-community"&gt;Building a Tech Community&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chico is a fun loving, community oriented town, a place where it’s easy to build relationships, so it’s only natural that our emerging tech community have a space that embodies that spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Erin told me, “part of what makes Open Source work is that it’s social. This is a social setting. People come here to have fun and hang out with their friends and to build cool stuff. 
So maybe on Friday night instead of going out and taking three shots of the cheapest whiskey they got on the shelf, let’s all go work on our laser shooting robot helicopter.” Many 
important innovations have historically come out of that same spirit of playfulness, which is one of the reasons I’m so excited about the emergence of this space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Idea Fab Labs has the potential to be a hub of innovation and entrepreneurial activity in Chico and the North State region. With such a wide variety of equipment available, it will likely 
become a crossroads of sorts for groups of people that may not ordinarily interact or work together. I would argue that the most interesting ideas come from a multidisciplinary approach 
that will be enabled by this type of cross pollination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you at the lab!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Community Summit Summup</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2013/02/25/community-summit-summup/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/02/25/community-summit-summup/</id>
    <published>2013-02-25T14:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-02-25T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Zingg engages frats" height="200" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/zingg-frats.jpg" width="300" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four hundred people representing virtually every part of the Chico community attended a gathering on the Chico State campus last Friday to collaborate on actions we can take
to change Chico’s increasingly out-of-control drinking culture. Attendees ranged from the Chico State and Butte College student bodies, fraternities and sororities, parents 
and University officials, to members of the Chico City Council, Chico Police and EMTs, to downtown bar owners, retail sellers of alcohol, apartment building owners, as well 
as a healthy dose of average Chico community members like me.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Zingg engages frats" height="200" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/zingg-frats.jpg" width="300" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four hundred people representing virtually every part of the Chico community attended a gathering on the Chico State campus last Friday to collaborate on actions we can take
to change Chico’s increasingly out-of-control drinking culture. Attendees ranged from the Chico State and Butte College student bodies, fraternities and sororities, parents 
and University officials, to members of the Chico City Council, Chico Police and EMTs, to downtown bar owners, retail sellers of alcohol, apartment building owners, as well 
as a healthy dose of average Chico community members like me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were greeted with a seating arrangement of large, concentric ovals, immediately giving off a collaborative feel rather than a lecture hall. Paul Zingg, the President of 
Chico State, set the tone by saying “action without understanding has no meaning. Understanding without action has no consequence. We’re talking about trying to understand 
and to act in a meaningful and consequential way to address issues that connect us. We’re not here to wring hands in frustration and desperation. We’re not here to wag our 
fingers and lecture, and we’re certainly not here to point our fingers in blame. We are here to connect, and communicate, and commit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the introductory speeches, we were introduced to a professional mediator brought in to facilitate the conversations. I must admit, I was skeptical at first. She had 
a serious hippy mediator vibe and used a lot of fuzzy language. She introduced us to what she called “open space technology,” which is like the Montessori of meeting formats, 
as in, this is your meeting, follow your passion. It starts with anyone and everyone proposing a topic, getting up and giving a one or two sentence introduction to their topic, 
and posting it on a giant bulletin board of sorts. I was surprised to see so many people jump up and propose topics for discussion. There was so much passion and interest in 
this topic and everyone seemed to have ideas to bring to the table. Some in attendance scoffed at the proposed methodology at first, but in the end, it worked beautifully, 
and I think everyone felt like they had their chance to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were three sessions in all, with each session divided into several breakout groups discussing a given topic. Topics included “Why should the University recognize frats 
at all?”, “The role of the media and advertising”, “How can local business help?”, “Early intervention in K-12 and the importance of parental 
responsibility”, and “Alcohol and sexual assault”. Each of these discussions was vibrant—full of intelligent ideas and well-informed, respectful dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was most interested in hearing from students. I believe any true change in student culture must be driven by the students themselves. I’m not 18 anymore, but I remember 
well that this is an age defined largely by opposition to parents and authority figures. Nobody likes being told what to do, but this is especially true when you are in 
college and forging your identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the students in attendance, the majority seemed to be either from, affiliated with, or defending the fraternities and sororities. Numerous sulking frat dudes wore their 
letters and sat with bored expressions and arms crossed, unhappy at having to deal with what has become an existential crisis. The Greek system has been suspended since last 
semester after numerous accounts of hazing at several fraternities, and the death of Mason Sumnicht, a pledge to Sigma Pi, after a night of heavy drinking on his 21st birthday. 
They are to be reinstated next month if they agree to a set of strict guidelines to prevent violence and alcohol abuse. One breakout session was led by a community member that 
asked why frats should be recognized by the University at all. His main point was that this is a relatively small percentage of the student population that is directly or 
indirectly involved in a disproportionately high percentage of dangerous situations, such as alcohol poisonings, brutal hazings, and student deaths. This naturally drew an 
audience consisting largely of fraternity and sorority leadership and membership, in which they attempted to persuade us that they do a lot of good, raising money for charity 
and so on. They attempted to deflect by saying that technically their houses are dry, and that they don’t throw parties where alcohol is served. I’ll leave it up to you to 
decide if you believe that or not. At one point, Paul Zingg joined the conversation and had a poignant declaration: “Be who you say you are. There are no more second chances. 
This is it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were other bright students in attendance who brought a fresh perspective. Liza Worden, from the student groups CAVE (Community Action Volunteers in Education) and 
SAVE (Students Against Violence Everywhere), sat in on the breakout group dedicated to how local business can help. She said, “One of the first things I did when I came 
here was to get involved with volunteer work in the community. I felt like ‘oh wow, I belong to this community, there are adults out there that care about what I’m doing 
and appreciate what I’m doing.’ That very first connection made me feel like Chico was my home, rather than just a place where I’m going to school. Whether it be volunteer 
work, or recreational activities, or feeling connected to a certain business or entity in the community, or an actual internship or job (which would be prime for the students) 
that’s the best way to get them invested in the community and feel like this is their home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t agree more. We need a much deeper integration between the Chico business and arts communities and the student body, providing not just internships where they are 
treated as free labor, but long term mentorships. This not only provides productive channels for youthful energy that might otherwise be put into a night of drinking, but 
it provides a deeper connection and incentive to stay in Chico, growing the local economy and building a virtuous cycle of creative energy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bitcoin - Don't Believe The Hype</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2013/02/11/bitcoin-don-t-believe-the-hype/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/02/11/bitcoin-don-t-believe-the-hype/</id>
    <published>2013-02-11T19:13:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-02-11T19:13:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right plain" alt="Bitcoin" height="225" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/bitcoin.png" width="225" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin, the new decentralized digital currency that’s rapidly gaining popularity, was invented in 2008 by a mysterious hacker named Satoshi Nakamoto. 
He published the original paper describing the protocol, developed the initial implementation, and remained active on the mailing lists until mid-2010, 
but then vanished. He was presumed to be an individual from Japan, but nobody by that name actually exists, so many now assume Nakamoto is a pseudonym 
for an individual or group that wished to remain secret. So what did this mysterious person/group/ghost create, and why is it taking the world by storm?
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right plain" alt="Bitcoin" height="225" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/bitcoin.png" width="225" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin, the new decentralized digital currency that’s rapidly gaining popularity, was invented in 2008 by a mysterious hacker named Satoshi Nakamoto. 
He published the original paper describing the protocol, developed the initial implementation, and remained active on the mailing lists until mid-2010, 
but then vanished. He was presumed to be an individual from Japan, but nobody by that name actually exists, so many now assume Nakamoto is a pseudonym 
for an individual or group that wished to remain secret. So what did this mysterious person/group/ghost create, and why is it taking the world by storm?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin is essentially a new form of money, purely digital and stored on your computer. It can be treated like cash, and payments in any denomination 
can be made securely and instantly around the world. It is managed and operated by a peer-to-peer network, so no central authorities or banks are involved 
in these transactions. It is anonymous, so you can buy and sell whatever you want without leaving a trace. This has led to its popularity on underground 
markets such as Silk Road, where bitcoins are used to buy drugs, weapons, stolen credit cards, assassination contracts, basically whatever you can think of. 
Because of this anonymity, bitcoin transactions are not generally reported to tax authorities, making them tax-free (at least for now). Transactions are 
secured by strong public-key cryptography, a very secure mechanism, although it does ultimately depend on the security of your individual computer. If 
someone hacks your computer, your bitcoins can be stolen, in the same way that someone can steal cash out of a safe if your house is not properly secured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the features of the currency from a user perspective, but what about from a systemic perspective? The primary feature that bitcoin advocates are 
excited about is the absence of any central authority. There is no central bank managing the currency, as opposed to virtually every government currency, 
where a national or regional bank, such as the Federal Reserve or European Central Bank, controls the amount of money in circulation. Proponents are excited 
by this because of perceived mismanagement of U.S. dollars by the Federal Reserve, in conjunction with out-of-control government spending that has led to 
unprecedented levels of “printing” in recent years. Fears that the government will be unable to control its spending, leading to high rates of inflation, 
make a deflationary currency scheme like bitcoin seem very attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do bitcoins get created? The technical details of the money creation process are a little too arcane to describe quickly or easily, but if you’re 
technically minded, the protocol is open source and available online. Bitcoins are created in a controlled fashion, at a predictable rate, essentially as 
a reward for the computational work required to keep the system running. Since this is a peer-to-peer network, it requires a large number of computers 
running at the same time to keep things running smoothly. This means capital and electricity costs for the participants, so as a reward, new bitcoins are 
given on a somewhat random basis to those doing the work. This is what puts bitcoins into the system. This process is called “bitcoin mining,” due to its 
similarity to gold mining—work is done to produce something of value and put it in circulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin mining is one of the primary drivers of the hype behind bitcoin. Unsuspecting newcomers are led to believe that all they have to do is run a 
computer program 24/7, and it will essentially print money. There are numerous sites and blogs describing “mining rigs”—people building out elaborate 
specialized computers and networks for the purpose of capturing this money as it is created. Now, before you go out and waste your money, I should tell 
you that the facts do not support the hype. There is so much computational power in the network at this stage that the likelihood of capturing any new 
coins is very low unless you have an enormous pool of computers at your disposal, and the costs of building and operating such a network will likely 
outpace your return. If you want to use bitcoin, do it for its utility, not out of hope of getting “free” coins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other way to get bitcoins is to trade national currencies for them. There are several online currency exchanges available, such as Mt. Gox, that 
allow you to trade dollars for bitcoins and vice-versa. This is another driver of the hype behind bitcoin—speculators that are essentially investing 
in bitcoins, hoping the value will go up, as it has been. The value is extremely volatile, and traders are capitalizing on that, but overall the value 
has been going up as more people buy into the hype. As of the time of this writing, one bitcoin is worth $22.76.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My analysis of bitcoin has led me to believe that the money creation process is flawed, and the system rewards early adopters to an unfair degree. It has 
some of the characteristics of a Ponzi scheme as a result. Early adopters have already captured about half of the total number of bitcoins that will ever 
be generated, and as the rest of us scramble, their value will increase. The deflationary aspect of this virtual currency is also troubling—it doesn’t 
account for the fact that, as the number of participants increase, the value of the overall economy also increases, but the money supply does not reflect 
that. Bitcoin is a very interesting experiment, but I believe it is the first of many, with much left to be desired.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hello, My Name is Chico, And I Have A Drinking Problem</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2013/01/21/hello-my-name-is-chico-and-i-have-a-drinking-problem/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/01/21/hello-my-name-is-chico-and-i-have-a-drinking-problem/</id>
    <published>2013-01-22T01:56:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-01-22T01:56:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right plain" alt="Chico Drinking" height="224" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/hello-chico.png" width="300" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mason Sumnicht, a pledge to Sigma Pi at Chico State, died on November 15th after a night of heavy drinking at local bars. He was celebrating his 21st birthday by drinking 21 shots with the help 
of his fraternity brothers. His life ended with severe brain damage and 12 days of life support in the hospital. The tragedy of the loss of a young man with his whole life ahead of him cannot be 
overstated. Unfortunately, such a tragic event is not as uncommon in Chico as it should be. This was the fourth alcohol-related student death in the fall semester—Shawn Summa, Brett Olson, 
and Carly Callaghan all lost their lives in the last four months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few of the highest profile cases in recent months, but the list goes on and on—drunk driving, hazings, sexual assaults, rapes, drownings, alcohol poisonings, stabbings—crimes 
related directly to the high rate of alcohol consumption by students and the community at large.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right plain" alt="Chico Drinking" height="224" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/hello-chico.png" width="300" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mason Sumnicht, a pledge to Sigma Pi at Chico State, died on November 15th after a night of heavy drinking at local bars. He was celebrating his 21st birthday by drinking 21 shots with the help 
of his fraternity brothers. His life ended with severe brain damage and 12 days of life support in the hospital. The tragedy of the loss of a young man with his whole life ahead of him cannot be 
overstated. Unfortunately, such a tragic event is not as uncommon in Chico as it should be. This was the fourth alcohol-related student death in the fall semester—Shawn Summa, Brett Olson, 
and Carly Callaghan all lost their lives in the last four months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few of the highest profile cases in recent months, but the list goes on and on—drunk driving, hazings, sexual assaults, rapes, drownings, alcohol poisonings, stabbings—crimes 
related directly to the high rate of alcohol consumption by students and the community at large.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chico has long cultivated a party culture, and if you look at our history, we go through cycles of increasingly uncontrolled behavior followed by public outcry and attempts to moderate it. 
There’s Pioneer Days, an annual week-long alcohol-fueled bacchanalia where anything that could happen, did. &lt;em&gt;Playboy&lt;/em&gt; dubbed Chico State America’s #1 party school in 1987, and that 
year the parties led to full-on riots, complete with street fires and overturned cars. The President of the school at the time, Robin Wilson, met with local officials, who agreed to shut down 
the event with police force, famously saying that he “took it out back and shot it in the head.” Then there’s the 2008 riots, when Chico Police attempted to break up a party 
at 6th &amp;amp; Cherry, and students retaliated and rioted downtown. Then there’s Halloween, which used to draw tens of thousands of people from all over the state for a massive street party, 
which then devolved into increasingly violent behavior until the festivities in 2001 saw four stabbings, 36 assaults (two sexual), two dozen car accidents and various acts of vandalism. This was 
followed by a crackdown the following year composed of 400 officers from across the North State, many on horseback, phalanxes of police walking the streets in groups of six to ten, DUI checkpoints, 
helicopters, and in later years advertisements run statewide featuring cops rounding up revelers and menacing voices saying “The party is over”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why the history lesson? This writer believes we are about to experience another crackdown. It’s not a very bold prediction. The President of the University, Paul Zingg, has already suspended 
the fraternities and sororities on campus, refusing to reinstate their charter until they agree to some yet-to-be-determined restrictions. In addition, he and other community leaders have 
published a &lt;a href="http://www.csuchico.edu/prs/documents/callforcommunityaction.pdf"&gt;call to action&lt;/a&gt; asking for everyone to work together to moderate alcohol consumption in Chico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is clearly a multifaceted issue that does not lend itself to a simple analysis or a single point of blame. Part of the issue, clearly, is that some students come to Chico State specifically 
because they want to party. It still has a reputation as a party school, despite the restrictions put in place since the ‘80s. Surveys show that 35% of incoming freshmen report participating 
in binge drinking during their senior year of high school, significantly higher than the national average of 22%. Once here, students report feeling pressure to drink heavily, and the culture 
created on campus, and to some extent throughout the community, certainly contributes to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shouldn’t be surprising that students predisposed to heavy drinking, immersed in a party culture, in a town where cheap alcohol is everywhere, will get themselves into trouble. 
The question is: what responsibility, if any, do the institutions and businesses we set up—the University, the City, downtown bars and clubs, and the community as a whole—have in 
helping students avoid truly dangerous situations, whether it be alcohol poisoning, hazing, or sexual assaults? Does it actually help to set up new rules and regulations, or will lasting change 
only come with a shift in culture?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve spoken with a dozen or so individuals, everyone from long-time residents, to students, to downtown bar owners, and I’m an ideas guy, so please allow me to synthesize these 
discussions into a few ideas. Hopefully this will stimulate further discussion and community resolve around achievable change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="fraternities"&gt;Fraternities&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must renew your commitment to brotherhood. Pressuring a brother to drink dangerous volumes of alcohol is a betrayal, as is providing alcohol to a brother once he has exceeded his body’s 
tolerance. Nobody wants to kill your party, but certainly a good time can be had by all without anyone dying. Take the time to learn the very real limitations of the human body and to detect 
dangerous levels of intoxication. You have a moral obligation, and if you don’t meet your responsibility, your charter will be revoked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="the-university"&gt;The University&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your primary role is one of education. Require a comprehensive health and safety course for all new students (freshmen and transfers) surrounding issues of excessive alcohol consumption, 
interactions between prescription pills and alcohol, and sexual assault prevention. Ensure that it’s interesting and fun so students actually want to attend and pay attention. 
Invite community members, bartenders, and former students who have dealt with the consequences of alcohol abuse to present their perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increase your academic standards. Eliminate curved grading. Hold more classes on Friday afternoons and Monday mornings. You are an academic institution that needs to take academics more seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erect a memorial in a prominent location to all those we’ve lost to drug and alcohol abuse. There is very little institutional memory among the student population. The high turnover rate 
means that new students don’t necessarily appreciate how dangerous excessive alcohol consumption can be. This constant reminder/buzzkill will help to counterbalance the pull of the drinking 
culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should bring local bar owners into the discussion. Notably missing from your call to action are the names of any local bar owners. I met with five who said they were never contacted or 
consulted prior to its publication, but would have welcomed the opportunity to participate in the discussion. I think you’ll find some unlikely allies if you approach the issue in a 
balanced way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="parents"&gt;Parents&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that 35% of incoming freshmen are already binge drinkers points to a glaring lack of parental guidance in the lives of these young people prior to their arrival. Parents must take an 
active role in discussing the dangers of excessive alcohol consumption. We clearly need to get the message across a lot sooner than we have been. Rather than burying your head in the sand and 
hiding behind blanket prohibitions, we need to realize that kids are getting into stuff earlier and earlier. Here in Chico, parties with alcohol are happening as early as middle school. Parents 
clearly have a huge role to play in monitoring their kids and talking about alcohol early and often, right alongside discussions of drug use (including prescription pills) and safe sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="bar-owners"&gt;Bar Owners&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a moral and legal obligation to bounce underage kids and to look all of your customers in the eye and cut them off if they’ve reached their limit. If you provide alcohol to someone 
that is clearly wasted, you have crossed the line from service provider to predator. The vast majority of Chico’s bar owners recognize this, and operate honest, legal businesses and take 
their responsibility seriously. However, some are playing fast and loose with their licenses—Riley’s served ten shots in 75 minutes to Mason Sumnicht the night he was hospitalized. 
Clearly, they fell short of their responsibility to cut off overly intoxicated customers that night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are not simply a small business meeting the demands of the market. Yours is a special case, where your customer’s demand may or may not be genuine. The first few might be, but as someone gets 
progressively hammered, their judgement has been compromised and you have an obligation to moderate their otherwise dangerous behavior. You are also in some cases dealing with a complicated group 
dynamic that is encouraging excessive consumption. Your role is to know when to serve and when to stop serving. It’s probably best to serve smaller quantities so you can keep an eye on 
things—serving pitchers of vodka is not going to give you the level of granularity you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="the-city"&gt;The City&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passing new laws or regulations is unlikely to have any effect. You don’t have the staff to enforce them! It is entirely likely that your attempt to further regulate alcohol consumption will 
have unintended side effects. One might argue that shutting down Pioneer Days, Halloween, and St. Patrick’s Day and forcing downtown bars out of business has simply pushed the problem 
elsewhere—to house parties that are completely impossible to regulate. We have plenty of laws already—your challenge is to find the resources to enforce them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="community-members"&gt;Community Members&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have a role to play in engaging University students, bringing them into the community, and offering constructive channels for their youthful energy as an alternative to constant partying. 
This will not only help moderate dangerous levels of alcohol consumption, but can also serve the long term interests of students and the community at large. Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economy is in pretty sore shape. We all recognize the need to revitalize and grow local business. We have a student population that for the most part comes here from other areas, parties hard, 
and leaves in four years, with very little long-term benefit accruing to the community. We ought to be able to pick the best and brightest among them and recruit them to stay here, start businesses, 
and help our community prosper. We can do this by creating an incubator for startups composed of the most talented and driven students, supplemented by experienced entrepreneurs from the community. 
For example, if we want to grow the web/mobile software sector in Chico, we incubate companies composed of Computer Science, Communication Design and Business students, with mentorship, support, 
or possibly leadership from those in the community with relevant industry experience. This would not only give students valuable experience starting a company while in college, but hopefully would 
help them establish long-term roots in Chico and grow our local economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few ideas. We at the Synthesis hope to engage the community in depth on this issue over the course of the next few months, and facilitate an ongoing conversation that will hopefully 
remain constructive and focused on achievable change. Please contact us with any insights or ideas you have on this very important topic.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Brief Year In Review</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2012/12/31/a-brief-year-in-review/"/>
    <id>/blog/2012/12/31/a-brief-year-in-review/</id>
    <published>2013-01-01T01:56:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-01-01T01:56:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;h5 id="open-source-hardware-on-the-rise"&gt;Open Source Hardware On The Rise&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Limor Fried" height="320" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/limor_fried_sm.jpg" width="192" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limor Fried, the fearless leader of the open source hardware movement, and an inspiration to makers and hackers worldwide, has been &lt;a href="http://www.entrepreneur.com/article/225213"&gt;named Entrepreneur of the Year&lt;/a&gt; 
by &lt;em&gt;Entrepreneur&lt;/em&gt; magazine, and I can’t think of a more appropriate recipient. Last year, her company Adafruit Industries sold $10 million worth of DIY open-source electronic hardware kits. 
With 200,000 customers, she has inspired a new movement of hackers and makers to treat circuits and electronics in the same way open-source software designers have been treating code for decades. 
Publishing your designs and encouraging others to use and improve upon them has proven to be a major force in the software world, and this same community effort has now come to the hardware world 
as well. I am part of a nascent maker community here in Chico that has been putting Adafruit products to use, collaborating freely and publishing our designs and source code for others to build on, 
and I believe this exciting trend is here to stay.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h5 id="open-source-hardware-on-the-rise"&gt;Open Source Hardware On The Rise&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Limor Fried" height="320" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/limor_fried_sm.jpg" width="192" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limor Fried, the fearless leader of the open source hardware movement, and an inspiration to makers and hackers worldwide, has been &lt;a href="http://www.entrepreneur.com/article/225213"&gt;named Entrepreneur of the Year&lt;/a&gt; 
by &lt;em&gt;Entrepreneur&lt;/em&gt; magazine, and I can’t think of a more appropriate recipient. Last year, her company Adafruit Industries sold $10 million worth of DIY open-source electronic hardware kits. 
With 200,000 customers, she has inspired a new movement of hackers and makers to treat circuits and electronics in the same way open-source software designers have been treating code for decades. 
Publishing your designs and encouraging others to use and improve upon them has proven to be a major force in the software world, and this same community effort has now come to the hardware world 
as well. I am part of a nascent maker community here in Chico that has been putting Adafruit products to use, collaborating freely and publishing our designs and source code for others to build on, 
and I believe this exciting trend is here to stay.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One particularly interesting product to come out of the hardware world this year is a $35 credit card sized computer called &lt;a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/"&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/a&gt;. Hailing from the UK, this 
tiny computer is a fully featured open source Linux box with very capable specs. They are made by the Raspberry Pi Foundation, a nonprofit formed to help reverse the declining interest in 
Computer Science, and get kids hacking again. A vibrant, loyal community has formed, using these systems in surprising ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="d-printers-go-mainstream"&gt;3D Printers Go Mainstream&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Replicator" height="193" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/replicator2.png" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D printing is the process of manufacturing solid objects using a 3D computer model and a device that adds layers of material (usually plastic) until the model has taken shape in the real world. 
This technology has been around for years, but 2012 is a turning point in refinement and accessibility. &lt;a href="http://www.makerbot.com/"&gt;Makerbot&lt;/a&gt;, a Brooklyn company, has released the 
&lt;a href="https://store.makerbot.com/replicator2.html"&gt;Replicator 2&lt;/a&gt;, a turnkey desktop 3D printer that uses biodegradable plastic for its source material. It has a resolution of 0.1mm and is able to 
produce high-fidelity models of virtually anything you can imagine. It’s almost like the first step toward the &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; replicator, except everything comes out plastic. Hey, you have to 
start somewhere… It costs around $2,000, bringing this device to a much broader audience than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a move that will truly make 3D printing mainstream, the office supply company &lt;a href="http://blog.makezine.com/2012/12/03/staples-rolling-out-pilot-3d-printing-service/"&gt;Staples has announced that it will begin offering 3D printing services&lt;/a&gt;
at its stores. They will be using a high-end device by MCOR that uses paper as its source material, with about the same resolution as the Makerbot Replicator. It may sound odd to use paper, but the 
resulting objects are stunningly detailed and realistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are people using this technology? Designers prototype new products without going through an expensive machining process or lengthy turnaround with a Chinese manufacturer for each iteration. 
Researchers produce models of delicate artifacts. Artists apply their creativity to a new medium and inventors extend their capabilities to produce an unlimited variety of objects cheaply and easily. 
Rather than relying solely on mass production, this technology makes decentralized manufacturing and collaborative innovation easier than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="obama-wins-with-help-from-big-data"&gt;Obama Wins With Help From Big Data&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Big Data" height="179" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/bigdata.png" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Obama campaign was widely praised in 2008 for its innovative use of social media to attract a wider audience, especially young people. But 2012 will be remembered as the beginning of the era of 
Big Data in presidential campaigns. Shortly after taking the job, Jim Messina, Obama’s campaign director, said “we are going to measure every single thing in this campaign.” 
He then went on to hire dozens of data analytics specialists and a Chief Scientist, Rayid Ghani, a prominent researcher in data mining and machine learning, to lead the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing they did was launch project &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/victory_lab/2012/02/project_narwhal_how_a_top_secret_obama_campaign_program_could_change_the_2012_race_.html"&gt;Narwhal&lt;/a&gt;—the 
creation of a single, massive database that merged information collected from pollsters, fundraisers, consumer databases, and social media, with the Democratic voter files in swing states. The purpose of 
this database wasn’t simply to provide contact information to compile call lists, but to run a series of tests on the effectiveness of certain messages on particular demographics. Traditional assumptions 
about voters were cast aside—instead, the campaign responded to measurements in the same way a web startup would adjust its marketing based on split testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This methodology and the resulting learnings were applied not only to fundraising (to the tune of $1 billion), but also to voter turnout. They developed incredibly sophisticated models on who was most 
likely to be persuaded, and who were most likely to persuade them, allowing them to focus their efforts in the right place. Big Data has entered the stage of presidential politics, and is here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Preparing The Littles For The Internet</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2012/12/10/preparing-the-littles-for-the-internet/"/>
    <id>/blog/2012/12/10/preparing-the-littles-for-the-internet/</id>
    <published>2012-12-11T01:56:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-12-11T01:56:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Nabi" height="250" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/nabi.png" width="250" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I asked my six-year-old what he hoped Santa would bring him for Christmas, he said “you know… It starts with an F… A phone!” When I informed him that he couldn’t have a phone 
until he was sixteen, he said “oh, well how about a computer?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably would have said the same thing if I were him, and he made the geek dad in me proud. Both the little mini-me’s are given supervised iPad time as a reward and they’ve grown quite 
fond of playing &lt;em&gt;Plants vs. Zombies&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Temple Run&lt;/em&gt; and watching Lego &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; stop motion animations or videos on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JdLCEwEFCMU"&gt;how to be a ninja&lt;/a&gt; or 
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FSijU52XJ7w"&gt;how to fold origami&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube. If I had that shit when I was six, I would want unrestricted access too.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Nabi" height="250" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/nabi.png" width="250" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I asked my six-year-old what he hoped Santa would bring him for Christmas, he said “you know… It starts with an F… A phone!” When I informed him that he couldn’t have a phone 
until he was sixteen, he said “oh, well how about a computer?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably would have said the same thing if I were him, and he made the geek dad in me proud. Both the little mini-me’s are given supervised iPad time as a reward and they’ve grown quite 
fond of playing &lt;em&gt;Plants vs. Zombies&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Temple Run&lt;/em&gt; and watching Lego &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; stop motion animations or videos on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JdLCEwEFCMU"&gt;how to be a ninja&lt;/a&gt; or 
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FSijU52XJ7w"&gt;how to fold origami&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube. If I had that shit when I was six, I would want unrestricted access too.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the holidays are here, I began wondering what was the most appropriate way to introduce my kids to the web without just handing them the keys to Google. I’m firm in my belief that web 
access is a fundamental human right at this point in civilization. The web is such a powerful tool for self-directed learning that I don’t want to wait too long to give it to my kids. However, 
it’s also like a modern mashup of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Library_of_Alexandria"&gt;Library of Alexandria&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Bazaar,_Istanbul"&gt;Grand Bazaar of Istanbul&lt;/a&gt;, 
and the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_Wallen"&gt;Red Light District&lt;/a&gt; of Amsterdam. Everything on Earth is represented on the web and Google has flattened it and made it all instantly accessible, not to 
mention the inherent linked structure of the web leads to all kinds of accidental, sometimes serendipitous, sometimes unfortunate, discoveries. Porn, people, I’m talking about porn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m not about to give a six-year-old a computer, but there are an impressive number of kid-friendly options out there right now. The best that I’ve seen is an Android tablet designed 
for kids called the &lt;a href="http://www.nabitablet.com"&gt;Nabi 2&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a powerful 7” tablet, similar in specs to the Nexus 7, but is has a customized operating system with two modes—parent mode and kid mode. Parents 
have full access to the latest Android OS, but kids have a simpler sandboxed interface, showing them only those apps approved by parents and a set of kid-friendly websites in a browser that doesn’t 
allow navigation off-site. It comes with a whole slew of prepackaged games and educational software, streaming music and age-appropriate TV. It doesn’t have access to Google Play, so app options 
are limited to Nabi’s built-in app store, which currently contains about 500 kid-friendly apps, and the Amazon Appstore which contains thousands more. It has a camera, which means the kids can 
take pictures and even Skype with their grandparents (or, more likely, each other from opposite ends of the house). And it comes with a robust protective bumper so you don’t have to worry so 
much about damage when the inevitable occurs. It runs for $199 at &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Fuhu-NABI-NABI2-NV7A-7-Inch-Tablet/dp/B008DBI5RI/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1355372519&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; or 
&lt;a href="http://www.nabitablet.com"&gt;nabitablet.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a relief to know that I’m not the only one thinking about how best to balance access to technology with an age-appropriate, phased introduction. We’ve got a couple of Nabis 
on the way and I think this is exactly the tool we need to start the process.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Kids Can Hack, Too</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2012/11/26/kids-can-hack-too/"/>
    <id>/blog/2012/11/26/kids-can-hack-too/</id>
    <published>2012-11-27T01:56:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-11-27T01:56:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Mindstorms" height="288" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/mindstorms.png" width="250" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been blessed with two bright, young boys with inquisitive and capable brains. The oldest is reaching an age where he’s asking more questions about my work, and when I use terms like 
programming, software, algorithms, or languages, his curiosity is piqued, but when I tell him that I can make a computer do anything I want, he really perks up. “Can you make a computer that 
shoots lasers?” Why yes, yes I can. “Can you make your phone shoot lasers?” Probably, I say, noting the extremely impressed look on my son’s face. (The problem is, now 
he’s going to want a demonstration.)
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Mindstorms" height="288" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/mindstorms.png" width="250" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been blessed with two bright, young boys with inquisitive and capable brains. The oldest is reaching an age where he’s asking more questions about my work, and when I use terms like 
programming, software, algorithms, or languages, his curiosity is piqued, but when I tell him that I can make a computer do anything I want, he really perks up. “Can you make a computer that 
shoots lasers?” Why yes, yes I can. “Can you make your phone shoot lasers?” Probably, I say, noting the extremely impressed look on my son’s face. (The problem is, now 
he’s going to want a demonstration.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the best way to introduce your child to computer programming, to bring them to that first gratifying moment when you communicate with the machine and hold its power in your hands, when you 
realize that your creative power is only limited by your own imagination? It’s a heady moment, and then you’re hooked. For me, that didn’t come until college, but I want to 
expose my boys to this creative outlet much earlier, give them the tools and guidance and see what comes of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developed by the MIT Media Lab, &lt;a href="http://scratch.mit.edu/"&gt;Scratch&lt;/a&gt; is a programming toolkit for kids 6 and up. It’s designed primarily for creating animated art, stories, or simple games. &lt;em&gt;Scratch&lt;/em&gt; is 
to kids now what &lt;a href="http://el.media.mit.edu/logo-foundation/logo/programming.html"&gt;Logo&lt;/a&gt; was when I was a kid—the clearest example of an educational framework for teaching computer science to kids. 
It’s a visual programming environment that’s very easy to get started with. With almost three million projects uploaded by the community, there is a lot of inspiration to draw from and 
support if you get stuck on something. It’s a great way to get your kids started with programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackety.com/"&gt;Hackety Hack&lt;/a&gt; differs from &lt;em&gt;Scratch&lt;/em&gt; in that it uses a real-world language that professionals use every day, Ruby. It’s an online tutorial framework that is designed for entry 
level programmers, including, with some guidance, youth coming to it for the first time. With &lt;em&gt;Hackety Hack&lt;/em&gt;, a Ruby tutorial is integrated with a text editor, so you write and run real programs 
as you go. New lessons are contributed by a nascent open source community that has a lot of promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://mindstorms.lego.com/"&gt;Lego Mindstorms&lt;/a&gt; is a robotics kit by Lego, also with roots in the MIT Media Lab. It comes with a programmable microcontroller, sensors, motors, and an easy-to-use programming toolkit to 
build your own autonomous robots. I’m pretty sure Santa has his eye on it this year. That, and a laser.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Dirty Kids</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2012/11/05/the-dirty-kids/"/>
    <id>/blog/2012/11/05/the-dirty-kids/</id>
    <published>2012-11-06T01:56:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-11-06T01:56:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Homeless" height="250" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/homeless.jpg" width="250" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The increasing size of the homeless population downtown has become a hot button political issue for Chico, and one that divides the candidates for the City Council election tomorrow. At the League of Women 
Voters forum on October 15th, I saw two very distinct points of view represented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was best illustrated by the comments of Sean Morgan, perhaps the most plain spoken conservative of the group advocating for new laws against objectionable behavior. In response to a question 
about what the city should do about the homeless “situation” downtown, Mr. Morgan replied, “My take is to give the police department the tools it needs—the misdemeanor vagrancy 
and panhandling laws they’ve asked the council for before and been denied. We have terrific resources for the disabled—the Jesus Center, the Torres Center, that help people get traction as long 
as they’re making progress, and they do a great job. To the others, I would like Chico to send a clear message, if you want to come to Chico to learn, add value and make progress, you’re welcome 
here, but if you’re here solely to party or bask endlessly in the generosity of our nonprofits, we ask that you move along.” That’s how you say “run ‘em out of town, boys” 
in 2012. The audience reacted with hushed gasps of shock on one side and beaming pride on the other.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Homeless" height="250" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/homeless.jpg" width="250" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The increasing size of the homeless population downtown has become a hot button political issue for Chico, and one that divides the candidates for the City Council election tomorrow. At the League of Women 
Voters forum on October 15th, I saw two very distinct points of view represented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was best illustrated by the comments of Sean Morgan, perhaps the most plain spoken conservative of the group advocating for new laws against objectionable behavior. In response to a question 
about what the city should do about the homeless “situation” downtown, Mr. Morgan replied, “My take is to give the police department the tools it needs—the misdemeanor vagrancy 
and panhandling laws they’ve asked the council for before and been denied. We have terrific resources for the disabled—the Jesus Center, the Torres Center, that help people get traction as long 
as they’re making progress, and they do a great job. To the others, I would like Chico to send a clear message, if you want to come to Chico to learn, add value and make progress, you’re welcome 
here, but if you’re here solely to party or bask endlessly in the generosity of our nonprofits, we ask that you move along.” That’s how you say “run ‘em out of town, boys” 
in 2012. The audience reacted with hushed gasps of shock on one side and beaming pride on the other.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other side was best illustrated by Tami Ritter, who said “it’s going to take a collaborative approach, both with Butte County Department of Behavioral Health as well as a variety of other 
service organizations, including the city. What I continue to hear is that we are legislating too much, and we are taking away individual freedoms, yet I continue to hear about how we need more legislation 
to make it illegal to panhandle or illegal to sit on the sidewalk or to sleep on the sidewalk. So I don’t think this is an issue or a problem that we can legislate away. I think this is something that 
is going to take a well thought-out approach.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consensus among the conservatives running for City Council seems to be that the presence of homeless people downtown hurts business traffic so we need new laws to criminalize their unwanted behavior. 
The consensus among the liberals seems to be that this is a complicated problem that cannot be legislated away, but requires a collaborative, multi-dimensional effort to get at the root problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt that what was missing from the debate was any indication that any of these candidates (with the exception of Tami Ritter, the founding director of the &lt;a href="http://www.chicoshelter.org/"&gt;Torres Shelter&lt;/a&gt;) has spent any time in contact 
with the subject of their speculation. How can a politician make such an important decision regarding an already marginalized segment of our community without having talked to them? Just as importantly, 
how can I, as a citizen, know who to support unless I put my own assumptions to the test? So, over several days, I spent time talking with homeless persons in downtown Chico in an effort to understand this 
misunderstood and marginalized part of our community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toby Schindelbeck, another conservative candidate for City Council, correctly identified four segments of the homeless population that have different characteristics and different needs. At the candidate forum, 
he said “you have the homeless that are down on their luck from the economy, and they’re homeless because of that. You have the people that are mentally ill or vets, and both those categories need 
our help. And then we have the street life enthusiasts, who choose the lifestyle. They travel on the homeless highway from Seattle to Portland to San Francisco, and now Chico is on that stop. And then we have 
the AB109 early releases who are the most dangerous out of all of them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, when the average citizen or politician in Chico talks about the “homeless problem downtown,” they are most likely talking about the travelers—the young travelers with backpacks, often 
accompanied by dogs, sitting in front of businesses with provocative signs asking passersby for “spare change.” They are the most visible and noisy of the homeless that the average citizen in Chico 
comes in contact with, and therefore the most politically visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two I spoke to in front of Jamba Juice, Charlie and Red, called themselves “dirty kids.” Red had tattoos on his calves: “Clean kids get sick and die. Dirty kids get sick and live.” 
They painted a romantic picture of life on the road, a carefree life of no responsibilities, near constant partying, traveling all over the country, living outdoors. Charlie had face tattoos and a scar on her 
chest from a heart surgery. She had a dog that was “born in the snow—I hitched 250 miles to save her, and now she’s mine.” She had an ebullient, dynamic, joyful personality and a charming 
smile. Born near Seattle, she has been homeless since age 14, on the road for 12 years off and on. Of all the traveling kids I spoke to, she had the most romanticized notion of life on the road. She dropped out 
of school early, and briefly went back to try to finish high school, but when her grades were failing and she told her high school counselor all she wanted to do was travel, he told her to just drop out and do it. 
So she did. She loves the freedom, but also looks back with almost wistful memory of her previous life—her room filled with old Victorian things, a 1920s top hat, beautiful tapestries and little gold trinkets, 
not to mention a comfortable bed. Whenever she gets a chance to cook in a kitchen, as she did recently when she cooked biscuits and gravy for a group of traveling kids, she has “secret housewife fantasies. 
I clean the kitchen and cook for everyone and I just love the smell of the kitchen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red is a bit older, from Pennsylvania, and has been on the road for twelve years. He has red hair and scruffy mutton chops and a broken front tooth. He is polite, respectful, and kind. He did not become homeless 
by choice, but began associating with the traveling kids, picking up tips on where to get food and how to make ends meet. He said “some of those kids give the rest of us a bad name, but aside from being a 
little noisy at night when we’re hanging out partying, we don’t cause any trouble.” He doesn’t want to go back to a traditional life “paying rent for something I’ll never own” 
and rarely stays in one place for more than a few weeks. He said “about 15-20 of us sleep in the plaza at night. They’re all a lot like us. We’ve even seen a lot of them in other towns. It’s 
funny—it’s a small world, and we’ll see the same people again and again all over.” Asked where they’ve been recently, he mentions “Seattle, Portland, Bend, Klamath Falls, San Francisco, 
but Chico is an excellent place to winter.” As we were talking, a friend came by to share a portion of a breakfast burrito from a nearby trashcan. “People throw away all kinds of good food, 
it’s crazy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digger is not a traveling kid—at least not anymore. I found him sitting in front of an empty storefront on Broadway. He was born in the area, became homeless at 14, and traveled for many years but came back 
to handle a legal problem and decided to stay. He said “the traveling kids ruin it for everyone. Everyone blames the ‘homeless’ but we’re all different.” He talked about trying to get 
a job and becoming bewildered because he doesn’t know his Social Security number and the unemployment office wanted it, as well as a passport, which he deemed ridiculous. He also pointed out a common, and 
very basic, problem for homeless individuals—handling the security of your possessions. He complained about how “punk teenagers and middle schoolers will come in to your camp and scatter all your stuff 
or steal from you.” He said it’s impossible to go to the shelters without a partner without being subject to theft. I heard this from virtually everyone I spoke to, and it is yet another impediment to 
getting anything done—seeking services at government offices or shelters, finding work—how do you keep your important, if few, belongings safe? Digger’s immediate environment was clean and orderly. 
He had a small backpack and a small suitcase with wheels with everything neatly contained. “If you don’t have everything tidy and ready to go when the police arrive, there will be trouble.” He 
showed disdain for those that make a mess in front of businesses and said he will “clean up messes left by the traveling kids to avoid any trouble.” Every few days or so, “I save up enough for a 
room somewhere to get a shower and a good night’s sleep.” As for why we are seeing an increase in travelers, Digger says that “towns all over are pushing people out, so people come here thinking 
it’s a party town, trash the place and move on.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob is a Korean War veteran who receives benefits through Veterans Affairs, but not enough to afford a place to live. He supplements his income by “doing this,” he said as he waved his arms indicating 
his wheelchair and cardboard sign. He was dressed cleanly, and had just been to the hospital, evidenced by the admission band still on his wrist. The night before, he was near a restaurant when the owner came out 
with a whole pizza, and another passerby offered him a burrito. It was too much food for him alone, so he shared it with “the asshole kids over by the 7-11.” He went back to the restaurant and slept 
there overnight, waking up “showered with $1 bills. They were everywhere, I guess people felt really generous last night.” Bob is aware of local politics and quite critical of the city. “They need 
to come down here and give people jobs, make new jobs.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John has been on the streets of Chico for 28 years. His face is weathered, and he has a speech condition that make it difficult for him to speak clearly. He is a survivor of a case of colon cancer that required a 
permanent colostomy. His meager possessions are found beside him in a utility cart topped by a sign saying “canser (sic) survivor, disabled, need help”. Spend one minute with John and you’ll 
realize he’s the real deal: a disabled man with a crippling medical condition and no resources. He has no bank account. He’s on the street asking for compassion and help. Most of the time, he is 
ignored by passersby that find his presence to be an uncomfortable reminder of the underlying cruelty of nature. The rest of the time, he settles for pity and a few dollars or some leftovers. When asked what 
he thinks of the proposal by conservative candidates for city council to enact anti-panhandling and anti-vagrancy ordinances, he offers a cogent rebuttal: “They need to live for a year on the street with 
no money, no bank account, nobody backing them up, and then see what kind of laws they should pass. They have a way of making themselves better than poor people. They need to start thinking about other people 
and not just themselves.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are almost 2,000 homeless individuals in Butte County, and there is no single reason behind it. This is a diverse group of people, a microcosm of society as a whole. There are families that lose their 
source of income and are kicked out of their house. There are kids that come from abusive or neglectful families, so they run away and strike out on their own, never to return. There are kids that reject 
mainstream society and develop romantic notions of life on the road and soon find themselves so far removed that it is unthinkable to return. There are war veterans of all ages that can’t make ends 
meet or have difficulty assimilating back into society after their experiences on the battlefield. There are the mentally ill—also a broad category with many distinctions—just trying to survive 
day by day, but unable to hold down a job and so find themselves on the street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criminalization of sitting on the sidewalk, asking for help, or sleeping in public is a far too simplistic response. We need leaders with a broad vision that can ask the right questions and engage the entire 
community, not just law enforcement, in the solution. If we take the easy way out just because we don’t like the dirty kids, we’ll make life impossible for people like John or Bob that are in legitimate 
need and rely on our compassion for their survival. Passing a law to sweep people out of sight so our skills of compassion atrophy even further is no solution at all.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Collaborative Consumption and the Emerging Reputation Currency</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2012/10/15/collaborative-consumption-and-the-emerging-reputation-currency/"/>
    <id>/blog/2012/10/15/collaborative-consumption-and-the-emerging-reputation-currency/</id>
    <published>2012-10-16T01:56:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-10-16T01:56:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Collaborative Consumption" height="247" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/collaborative-consumption.jpg" width="250" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most exciting trends in the web startup world—for me, at least—is the growing number of companies in the so-called “collaborative consumption” space. These companies are 
using technology to reinvent market behaviors that are as old as human civilization itself—sharing, bartering, and trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get specific: I’m talking about tools that let you share your car with your neighbors (&lt;a href="http://www.getaround.com/"&gt;Getaround&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.zipcar.com/"&gt;Zipcar&lt;/a&gt;), tools from your garage 
(&lt;a href="http://www.streetbank.com/"&gt;Streetbank&lt;/a&gt;), or your couch or guest bedroom with visitors from around the world (&lt;a href="https://www.airbnb.com/"&gt;Airbnb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.couchsurfing.org/"&gt;Couchsurfing&lt;/a&gt;); tools 
that let you raise support for your next venture directly from your customers (&lt;a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/"&gt;Kickstarter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.indiegogo.com/"&gt;Indiegogo&lt;/a&gt;); online markets for handmade or restored 
goods (&lt;a href="http://www.etsy.com/"&gt;Etsy&lt;/a&gt;); tools that revolutionize education by enabling experts outside the university to teach courses online (&lt;a href="http://www.skillshare.com/"&gt;Skillshare&lt;/a&gt;).
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Collaborative Consumption" height="247" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/collaborative-consumption.jpg" width="250" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most exciting trends in the web startup world—for me, at least—is the growing number of companies in the so-called “collaborative consumption” space. These companies are 
using technology to reinvent market behaviors that are as old as human civilization itself—sharing, bartering, and trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get specific: I’m talking about tools that let you share your car with your neighbors (&lt;a href="http://www.getaround.com/"&gt;Getaround&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.zipcar.com/"&gt;Zipcar&lt;/a&gt;), tools from your garage 
(&lt;a href="http://www.streetbank.com/"&gt;Streetbank&lt;/a&gt;), or your couch or guest bedroom with visitors from around the world (&lt;a href="https://www.airbnb.com/"&gt;Airbnb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.couchsurfing.org/"&gt;Couchsurfing&lt;/a&gt;); tools 
that let you raise support for your next venture directly from your customers (&lt;a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/"&gt;Kickstarter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.indiegogo.com/"&gt;Indiegogo&lt;/a&gt;); online markets for handmade or restored 
goods (&lt;a href="http://www.etsy.com/"&gt;Etsy&lt;/a&gt;); tools that revolutionize education by enabling experts outside the university to teach courses online (&lt;a href="http://www.skillshare.com/"&gt;Skillshare&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’m also talking about modern versions of more traditional tools for participating in the market, that focus more on the local trade, and empowering the unemployed or underemployed: tools for 
hyperlocal buying and selling (&lt;a href="https://www.getyardsale.com/"&gt;YardSale&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://krrb.com/"&gt;Krrb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.zaarly.com"&gt;Zaarly&lt;/a&gt;); tools to find and hire trusted locals for odd jobs, or to get hired for 
piece work (&lt;a href="https://www.taskrabbit.com"&gt;TaskRabbit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://iamexec.com/"&gt;Exec&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What all these companies have in common is that they are in the process of disrupting the centralized global market, making it more democratic and decentralized by giving us tools to operate on a peer-to-peer 
basis. It’s an acknowledgment of the fact that there are a lot of creative, talented people sitting on the sidelines of this economy simply because a system hasn’t been designed to properly include 
them. It’s a reflection of the weak economy in the wake of the 2008 financial crisis, and the average family’s need to make their dollars stretch further. It’s also partly a reflection of a 
growing cultural rejection of individualistic consumer behavior, driven by mainstream advertising, that has been at the heart of the American economy for decades, and the desire to return to a more authentic, 
connected, way of life. It’s incredibly exciting to see the growth in the adoption of these apps. I believe we are at a tipping point that will ultimately bring us out of the economic collapse of 2008 
and yield a more vibrant, resilient economy and stronger communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of online social networks has broken down the psychological barrier to sharing information about ourselves online. People who ten years ago were hesitant to post pictures of themselves online and 
tell the world about themselves, their work, and their hobbies, now do so without a second thought. We now use these social networks not only to communicate with friends and family, but also with the 
community at large and even with people all over the world. It turns out, people want to share. These social networks, whether they exist in their current form ten years from now or not (most likely not), 
will form the foundation of this new economy, one based on trust and authentic relationships between producer and consumer, and not just faceless transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One aspect of this new economy I’ve been thinking about lately is the crucial role that reputation and trustworthiness will play. One of the things &lt;a href="http://www.omidyar.com/team/pierre-omidyar"&gt;Pierre Omidyar&lt;/a&gt;, 
the founder of eBay, was most proud of, was the fact that his company largely pioneered online trust and reputation by making its feedback and rating system a core part of the user experience. We might look back 
on it now as a relatively crude mechanism, but the implications were profound. Think about it: people started trusting random strangers around the world enough to send them goods through the mail before receiving 
payment, a fairly uncertain outcome at the time. The early eBay community was made up of trustworthy individuals that operated in an open, authentic way that engendered trust. Nowadays, eBay has lost the 
spirit that infused the early community, as it built features designed to please “power sellers”, essentially destroying the person-to-person authenticity and turning it into an automated impersonal 
experience. What we will need to grow the new sharing economy is a similar, but more comprehensive, measure of reputation that tells you at a glance if the person you are dealing with is trustworthy. This will 
likely be an aggregation of activity in various areas of your life, both online and offline—a kind of “karma score”. I’m keeping my eye on a company named &lt;a href="http://legit.co/"&gt;Legit&lt;/a&gt; 
that’s working on just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chico is full of creative, talented people with a wide variety of skills. Our community values regional self sufficiency and has a spirit of kindness and generosity that we are rightly proud of. If 
you’re interested in this subject, or have ideas about how to further the sharing economy in Chico, or anywhere else for that matter, &lt;a href="http://mattolson.com/contact"&gt;send me an email&lt;/a&gt;—I’d 
love to talk to you.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What is that loud sucking sound?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://mattolson.com/blog/2012/10/01/what-is-that-loud-sucking-sound/"/>
    <id>/blog/2012/10/01/what-is-that-loud-sucking-sound/</id>
    <published>2012-10-01T20:58:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-10-01T20:58:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Olson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Dirty Cloud" height="250" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/dirty-cloud.jpg" width="250" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt; just ran a &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/23/technology/data-centers-waste-vast-amounts-of-energy-belying-industry-image.html"&gt;series on the destructive impact of cloud computing&lt;/a&gt;. 
In it, they publish their findings on the energy consumption and environmental impact of the datacenters that work behind the scenes to power our favorite web and mobile apps, store our data with full 
redundancy and fault tolerance in perpetuity, and deliver our electronic communications. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="right" alt="Dirty Cloud" height="250" src="https://mattolson-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/dirty-cloud.jpg" width="250" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt; just ran a &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/23/technology/data-centers-waste-vast-amounts-of-energy-belying-industry-image.html"&gt;series on the destructive impact of cloud computing&lt;/a&gt;. 
In it, they publish their findings on the energy consumption and environmental impact of the datacenters that work behind the scenes to power our favorite web and mobile apps, store our data with full 
redundancy and fault tolerance in perpetuity, and deliver our electronic communications.  Another way to phrase that: the datacenters that allow us to kill time stalking people on Facebook or playing 
Words With Friends, that store the world’s largest single collection of cat videos on YouTube and our collective stream of consciousness on Twitter, and that deliver all that spam to your inbox 
each morning and store those email attachments from 1999 that you’ll probably never look at again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, I’m really not that cynical. The web has permanently altered our reality—socially, economically, politically, educationally—for the better. It’s made us more connected, 
knowledgable, and empowered than ever. We can’t give up on that—if anything, we need to accelerate it. But the industry can’t operate in a vacuum. We need to be able to justify our
clean image and operate in a socially and environmentally responsible manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 90% of the 30 billion watts of electricity consumed by datacenters worldwide is a pure waste. That waste is equivalent to the output of 27 nuclear power plants—enough to power 20.5 million U.S. homes.
That, to me, is staggering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does that waste come from? Three places. First, comatose servers. &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt; study found that three quarters of the servers examined were comatose—not doing any useful computation. 
They were old web apps that nobody really uses anymore but the owners aren’t quite ready to admit it, back office systems that are kept up and running out of fear because the engineers don’t 
even remember what they are there for anymore, or extra servers that are waiting for a spike in traffic that may never materialize. Second, underutilization. Due to poor or outdated architectural choices, 
more servers are commissioned than fully utilized. Third, poor datacenter planning, inadequate adoption of best practices for temperature management such as hot and cold rows. I have managed colocation 
services for my clients in many different datacenters over the years, and I can attest to the fact that some do a much better job than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can the industry do? First, understand your systems and consolidate wherever possible. Second, stop being a prima donna about bare metal performance and adopt virtualization. Adopt an agile, 
elastic approach to server commission. Finally, know when to throw in the towel. Don’t keep your servers up and running just because it’s cheap and you may need it somewhere down the road. 
Do you leave your lights on around the house when you’re not using them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to powering servers, it doesn’t matter if that bit represents a cat video, porn, your Facebook photos, or important medical research data. Even free apps aren’t really free. 
Somewhere out there in the “cloud”, there are thousands and thousands of servers humming away, making a loud sucking sound, draining the nation’s energy supply.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
